University of Arizona Agricultural Experiment Station papers 1891-1922
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
University of Arizona Agricultural Experiment Station papers 1891-1922
AZ 446
This collection includes financial and agricultural records, workbooks detailing research and experiments, incoming and outgoing correspondence of Director R.H. Forbes, and miscellaneous related items.
University of Arizona Agricultural Experiment Station
6 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
The Hatch Act of 1887 gave federal funds to each state, initially of $15,000 each, to land-grant colleges in order to create a series of agricultural experiment stations, focusing specifically in the areas of soil minerals and plant growth. The Hatch Act created the national Agricultural Experiment Station System which promoted and conducted agricultural research at land-grant institutions around the country. The research arm of the College of Agriculture, the Arizona Agricultural Experiment Station was founded in 1890 along with the School of Agriculture. The creation of this school was interrelated to the founding of the University of Arizona..
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series.
Series I: Experiments, Workbooks and Ledgers, 1891-1922
Series II: Correspondence, 1894-1915
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes financial and agricultural records, workbooks detailing research and experiments, incoming and outgoing correspondence of Director R.H. Forbes from 1894-1903, and miscellaneous related items. Ledgers cover 1894 to 1922. Agricultural records include planting at the various stations, field experiments, and readings of temperature, barometer, evaporation and terrestrial radiation, 1891 to 1903. Workbooks include research on mesquite, canaigre, sugar beets, soils, water, plants and dates. The collection also includes inventories of books and property belonging to the Stations and correspondence regarding the artesian well at Servoss, Cochise County, Arizona, 1913 to 1915.
Forbes, R.H.; University of Arizona -- History; University of Arizona -- Records and correspondence; University of Arizona. Agricultural Experiment Station -- Records and correspondence; Agriculture -- Arizona; Horticulture -- Arizona; Irrigation -- Arizona; Canaigre; Mesquite -- Arizona; Date palm -- Arizona; Sugar beet -- Arizona; Soils -- Arizona; Groundwater -- Arizona -- Cochise County; Agricultural experiment stations -- Arizona; Correspondence; Workbooks; Ledgers
Container List
- Experiements, Workbooks and Ledgers, 1891-1922; Series I:
  This series includes financial and agricultural records, workbooks detailing research and experiments, and miscellaneous related items. Ledgers cover 1894 to 1922. Agricultural records include planting at the various stations, field experiments, and readings of temperature, barometer, evaporation and terrestrial radiation, 1891 to 1903. Workbooks include research on mesquite, canaigre, sugar beets, soils, water, plants and dates.
  - Artesian Well at Servoss, Cochise County: Financial records. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Farm Labor Accounts. January 1912-March 1914 (Box 1)
  - Soil Sample Borings, #1-700, 2 volumes. (Box 1)
  - Weights of Canaigre Samples, 2 volumes. (Box 1)
  - "Laboratory Work for Class Beginning Chemistry," by C. B. Collingwood, includes "Culture Experiments." 1891 (Box 1)
  - Donations to Arizona University and Experiment Station. 1891-1898 (Box 1)
    Begins with "1 pr Wild Cats" from Schultz & Franklin of Tempe. Mostly seeds, plants, samples of an agricultural nature.
  - Date Palm Distribution cards (examples of records kept). (Box 1)
  - Examples from the early Card File of Herbarium holdings (specimens now in the UA Herbarium). (Box 1)
  - Workbooks. 1894-1896 (Box 2)
    No. 1-19 missing.
    20 Mesquite
    21 Mesquite and Canaigre
    22 Mesquite
    23 Mesquite
    24 Canaigre
    25 Canaigre
    26 Canaigre
    27 Canaigre
    28 Miscellaneous
    29 Canaigre
    30 Canaigre
    31 Canaigre
    32 Miscellaneous
    33 Canaigre
    34 Canaigre
    35 Canaigre
    36 Canaigre
    37 Canaigre
    38 Canaigre
    39 Canaigre
    40 Soils
    41 Milk (at Tempe)
    42 Milk
    43 Canaigre
    43a Soils
    44 Soils
    45 Canaigre
    46 Milk
    47 Soils
    48 Soils
    49 Canaigre
    50 Soils
    51 Canaigre
    52 Soils
    53 Sugar Beets
    54 Miscellaneous
    55 Soils
    56 Sugar Beets
    57 Canaigre
    57b Miscellaneous
    58 Water
    59 Canaigre
    60 Canaigre (for R. J. Kerr)
    61 Canaigre (for Anglo-American Canaigre Co.)
    62 Canaigre
    63 Soils
  - Workbooks. 1897-1904 (Box 3)
    64 Canaigre
    65 Soils
    66 Soils
    67 Soils
    68 Sugar Beets
    69 Canaigre
    70 Soils
    71 Canaigre (for Anglo-American Canaigre Co.)
    72 Soils
    73 Sugar Beets
    74 Water
    75 Miscellaneous
    76 Water
    77 Soils
    78 Water
    79 Canaigre
    80 Water
    (81 Missing)
    (82 Missing)
    83 Miscellaneous
    (84 Missing)
    85 Soils
    (86 Missing)
    87 Miscellaneous
    (88 Missing)
    89 Miscellaneous
    90 Water (for Elwood Mead)
    91 Water (Consolidated Canal)
    (92 Missing)
    93 Miscellaneous
    94 Water (Florence Canal; Gila River)
    95 Food
    96 Water (Colorado River)
    97 Water (Consolidated Canal)
    98 Miscellaneous
    99 Water (Irrigation)
    100 Fertilizers
    100b Miscellaneous
    101 Sugar Beets
    102 Dates; Miscellaneous
    103 Canaigre
    104 Miscellaneous
    105 Silt (Salt and Gila Rivers)
    106 Sugar Beets
    107 Silt (Colorado Rivers)
    108 Water
    109 Sugar Beets
    110 Soils
    111 Water
    (112 Missing)
    113 Miscellaneous
    (114 Missing)
    115 Water
    (116 Missing)
    117 Water (Gila River, 1903, Colorado River 1904)
    (118 Missing)
    (119 Missing)
  - Workbooks. 1904-1910 (Box 4)
    120 Miscellaneous
    121 Water
    122 Windmill
    (123 Missing)
    124 Water
    (125 Missing)
    (126 Missing)
    127 Miscellaneous
    128 Dates
    129 Dates
    130 Copper
    131 Copper
    132 Copper
    133 Forage Plants
    134 Water
    (135 Missing)
    135a Copper, Book 1
    136 Copper, Book 2
    136? Miscellaneous
    (137 Missing)
    138 Copper
    (139-143 Missing)
    144 Water
    (145 Missing)
    (146 Missing)
    Unnumbered:
    Honey Vinegar Experiments
    Canaigre: selection experiments to improve the root for tanning materials
    Canaigre: record of cultivated lots relative to chemical life history, etc., 1895-1896
    Canaigre: an experiment to determine its chemical life history, 1894-1895
    Specific gravity: dry matter experiments, 1907-1909
    Wool: investigations
    Cactus digestive experiments
    Dates
    Three blue notebooks by H. B. Slade and a folder
  - Experiment Station Record of Correspondence Requests, etc. June 1894-July 1895 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Apple, Tuscon, Station no. 1. 1891-1895 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Peaches, apricots, and almonds, Mesa, Station no. 3. 1895? (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "East and West Orchards." 1894? (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Soil Thermometers. 1898-1899 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Evaporation and Terrestrial Radiation. 1898-1903 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Barometer. 1898-1900 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Temperature. 1898-1900 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Grasses and Forage Plants, Phoenix, Station no. 2. 1896 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Field Experiments with Canaigre, Books I-II. 1897-1899 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - Canaigre, Phoenix, Station no. 2. 1895-1896 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Tobacco, Phoenix, Station no. 2. 1897 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Inventories. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Books, pamphlets, etc. in Experiment Station Library, Tucson.
    Property belonging to the Agriculture and Horticulture Departments of the Agriculture Experiment Station, Tucson.
    Property belonging to the Agriculture Experiment Station, Phoenix.
  - Miscellaneous Records. 1895-1897 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Forage Plants, 1895
    Sugar Beets, Tucson, 1897
    Sugar Beet Seed Distribution
    Tobacco, Tucson?, 1897
    Crown Knot greenhouse experiments, December 1897
  - Journal for the University of Arizona Agricultural College and Experiment Stations. January 1894-March 1895 (Volume 6)
    Also contains Ledger, 1899-1902
  - Ledger. July 1901-June 1905 (Volume 7)
  - Ledger. July 1905-Juny 1907 (Volume 8)
  - Ledger ("Adams Fund" only). 1906-1907 (Volume 9)
  - Ledger. July 1907-September 1922 (Volume 10)
  - Ledger. July 1908-1914/1915 (Volume 11)
  - Plant and Seed Introduction Cards. 1899-1913 (Box 12)
- Correspondence, 1894-1915; Series II:
  This series consists of the incoming and outgoing correspondence of R.H. Forbes, Director of the Agricultural Experiment Station at the University of Arizona and Dean of the College of Agriculture. This series is arranged chronologically and contents of folders are alphabetized by last name of sender. This series also contains general correspondence regarding the Artesian Well at Servoss, Cochise County, Arizona from 1913-1915.
  - Forbes, R.H., (1 of 3), 1894-1897 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Forbes, R.H., (2 of 3), 1894-1897 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Forbes, R.H., (3 of 3), 1894-1897 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Forbes, R.H., (1 of 4), 1900-1901 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Forbes, R.H., (2 of 4), 1900-1901 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Forbes, R.H., (3 of 4), 1900-1901 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Forbes, R.H., (4 of 4), 1900-1901 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Forbes, R.H., (1 of 3), 1902-1903 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Forbes, R.H., (2 of 3), 1902-1903 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Forbes, R.H., (3 of 3), 1902-1903 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Artesian Well at Servoss, Cochise County: General Correspondence, January 1913-June 1914 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Artesian Well at Servoss, Cochise County: General Correspondence, July-December 1914 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Artesian Well at Servoss, Cochise County: General Correspondence, January-June 1915 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Artesian Well at Servoss, Cochise County: Correspondence with Charles E. Boehm, June 1914-June 1915 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Artesian Well at Servoss, Cochise County: Correspondence with C.R. Fillerup, January-June 1915 (Box 15, Folder 6)